<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="RosaB&#233;n&#233;dite_KojiroMatsukata_19250601_-606081684938715521">
  <!-- le document XML, dans sa forme actuelle, n'est pas valide selon la syntaxe TEI:
       la structure d&#233;finie ici devrait contenir d'autres &#233;l&#233;ments -->
  <teiHeader>
    <!-- l'en-t&#234;te de notre document, contenant les m&#233;tadonn&#233;es -->
    <fileDesc>
      <!-- description du fichier encod&#233; et de sa source -->
      <titleStmt>
        <!-- titre du document -->
        <title>Lettre manuscrite de Rosa B&#233;n&#233;dite &#224; Matsukata (vers juin 1925). </title>
        <author>Rosa B&#233;n&#233;dite</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Production et pr&#233;paration du texte brut</resp>
          <persName>L&#233;a Saint-Raymond</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transformation automatique du texte brut vers le XML-TEI</resp>
          <persName>Les participant.e.s &#224; l'atelier "Mod&#233;liser et exploiter des corpus textuels" (ENS-PSL, campus d'Ulm)</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <!-- informations sur le document XML encod&#233; -->
        <publisher>ENS-PSL</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Paris (France)</pubPlace>
        <date>2023-03-26 16:02:14.464991</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <!-- informations sur la source: la lettre que l'on encode -->
        <bibl type="lettre">
          <author>Rosa B&#233;n&#233;dite</author>
          <title>Lettre manuscrite de Rosa B&#233;n&#233;dite &#224; Matsukata (vers juin 1925). </title>
          <date>1925-06-01</date>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>INHA</institution>
            <idno>INHA 260-262</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <!-- informations sur l'encodage :
           - tei:editorialDecl, d&#233;crivant la m&#233;thode de production du document XML 
           - tei:projectDesc, contexte de production du XML 
      -->
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Production de l'encodage XML r&#233;alis&#233;e automatiquement avec la librairie LXML de Python &#224; partir d'une version en texte brut de la correspondance de Matsukata</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>L'atelier "Mod&#233;liser et exploiter des corpus textuels" a donn&#233; lieu &#224; cet encodage.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <!-- informations non bibliographiques sur le document encod&#233; 
           cet &#233;l&#233;ment l&#224; sera compl&#233;t&#233; par:
           - un tei:particDesc, qui d&#233;crit tout.es les personnes ayant &#233;crit
             ou re&#231;u des lettres dans le corpus Matsutaka
           - un tei:settingDesc, qui d&#233;crit tous les lieux d'exp&#233;dition/destination
             des lettres du corpus Matsutaka
           ces &#233;l&#233;ments seront rajout&#233; dans le notebook du cours.
      -->
      <correspDesc>
        <!-- description de la correspondance -->
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName>Rosa B&#233;n&#233;dite</persName>
          <placeName>Paris</placeName>
          <date when="1925-06-01">1925-06-01</date>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName>Kojiro Matsukata</persName>
          <placeName>Kobe</placeName>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <!-- le corps du texte. il peut comporter un tei:front et un tei:back
         et doit comporter un tei:body, comprenant le corps du texte -->
    <body>
      <!-- le corps du texte -->
      <opener>
        <salute>Dear Mr. Matsukata, </salute>
      </opener>
      <p>We are very thankful to you for your sympathy in our great sorrow. You know what my dear father&#8217;s death means to us, it is even more painful as it was so unexpected and quick. He took cold, the 30th, was ill for a few days with what seems flu, not of a dangerous kind but the heart failed. He breathed very painfully and could not sleep, they gave him an injection of morphine and we were so hopeful to see him falling asleep peacefully with a quiet breathing. It seemed everything would change for the best the day after, but he died in his sleep without suffering, without knowing he was leaving us. For this we must be grateful as it would have been so hard for him otherwise. </p>
      <p>We are now very busy in arranging everything, perhaps it is better in our grief to have so much to do. </p>
      <p>I have seen last Wednesday M. Okada [ou Okala ? illisible] and the other gentleman from Yamanaka. Everything was arranged in a perfect order concerning your collections, stored in the Mus&#233;e Rodin. The pictures from the Hansen collection are on their way back from America, as father had no answer telling him if they were to be directed to Japan from San Francisco. For all these works MM. Yamanaka are expecting your answer to their cables to know where to send them. </p>
      <p>Concerning the sculptures by Rodin belonging to you, they can be kept in the museum, it would cost so much to send them to England better wait to send them directly to Japan when you choose to ask for them. Some of the ones you ordered lately and even the Porte de l&#8217;Enfer are not yet finished though it will not be very long before they are.</p>
      <p>In his last letter to you, Father asked you to what purchase he was to affect the 100.000 f he had received from you. As he had lately had some opportunities of buying interesting thinks for you he had waited some of these new purchases being already half engaged. </p>
      <p>Shall we affect half of this 100.000 f that is 50.000 f as an account for the sum which you still owe to the mus&#233;e Rodin for your last orders and shall we keep the other 50.000 f or part of them for the payment of these half made purchases? Will you tell us as soon as possible.</p>
      <p>Mme Le Mancel, my father&#8217;s secretary at the Mus&#233;e Rodin, who know everything concerning your collection here had been put in charge by my father to make the catalog of your works of art. This catalog is not far from being finished. It givers for each piece its dimensions, description, etc in the manner of all good museum catalogs and it was to be translated in English afterward. Father thought by this way that when your collection would be sent to Japan, you would have only to add to this complete catalogue the remaining works which you (?) in England. It would be then the quickest way to publish it for the opening of your great museum. </p>
      <p>Mme Le Mancel has given Mr. Yamanaka all informations concerning your works and has made lists and inventories for them. I think it is best to let her finish as soo as possible the catalogue, as she is capable and began to do under my father&#8217;s direction and supervision. What do you think about it? She has not yet received any fees for this work. </p>
      <p>I think it is all what I had to tell you concerning your collection. You know how my father was interested in it, it was a great joy for him. His own dear museum had always been so short of money and many a time could not he buy for it th works he would have wished and from to the admiration of the public. That it was for him a real and deep satisfaction to be able to choose beautiful things and to arrange a museum according to his taste and possibilities. </p>
      <p>Shortly before his last illness, I remember his coming home one, from a big public sale where had been sold at very high prices, works by the same artists selected for your collections but of a lesser interest than yours though so much more expensive. He was so pleased of the good bargain he had made for you, he enjoyed the thought that by so doing he could save your money to buy other works and increase still your museum. </p>
      <p>If ever I can be of any help to you concerning your museum or thing over here, I will do with great pleasure, the memory of your friendship with me beloved father is very strong in me. If you want to go on with your purchases of art works for your museum in France and if you want an adviser not only able but as honest and absolutely disinterested as was my own dear father, I know you will always find a friendly and intelligent help in M. Andr&#233; Dezarrois, whom my father has designated in his will to succeed to him in his museums and for whom not only had he a great affection but the highest esteem and regard. </p>
      <p>My mother still very weak after her past illness joins me in thanks and greetings, </p>
      <closer>
        <salute>Very sincerely, </salute>
        <signed>Rosa B&#233;n&#233;dite</signed>
      </closer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
